Xiao Datu.
肖大图
What are you doing?
干嘛
Sneaking around with something?
鬼鬼祟祟拿什么呢
What?
什么
N... nothing.
没 没拿啊
Wow,
哎呦
so expensive.
那么贵
Bought another art book?
又买画册了是不是
Can't you buy something useful?
你不能买点有用的吗
Like groceries, maybe?
买点菜也好啊
What are you up to?
你 你干嘛呢你
Honey, this...
老婆 这 这个
this art book
这个画册
has great collection value.
它很有收藏价值的
Value?
什么呀
Do you really think you're an artist
你真以为你是艺术家啊
or a collector?
收藏家啊
Let me tell you, Xiao Datu,
我告诉你 肖大图
when we got married,
当时我们结婚的时候
you said
你告诉我
you had a talent for painting,
你对画画有天赋
and I believed you.
我真信了
What have you
这么多年
accomplished over the years?
你混出个什么名堂来
I do have talent.
我有天赋的嘛
What talent?
你有什么天赋啊你
I have exceptional talent.
我天赋异禀的
Mom, I'm back.
妈妈 我回来了
Xiaohua!
小画
Xiaohua, you're back.
小画 你回来了
Sweetie, happy?
宝贝 开心吗
Yes, happy.
开心
Great, great.
真好 真好
Take a rest.
快休息休息
You must be tired, right?
累了对不对
Go ahead.
快去
Have some rest.
辛苦啊
Good job, Xiaohua.
辛苦啊 小画
Put your change outside.
把衣服放在外面
Okay.
好
I'll wash them later.
妈等会儿给你洗啊
Xiao Datu,
肖大图
listen to me!
我告诉你啊
I have
我给大家
good news for everyone.
宣布一个好消息
In the national physics competition,
这次呢 全国物理竞赛
our class's Ling Dong
咱们班凌冬同学
and Chen Luyang
和陈璐阳同学
won first
分别获得了一等奖
and second place, respectively.
和二等奖的好成绩
Let's congratulate them.
大家恭喜他们
All right,
好
I hope all students
希望同学们呢
will take them as examples
也以他们为榜样
and strive to be like them.
向他们看齐
Additionally,
另外
I have another announcement.
我再宣布一个事情啊
Our school has set up
咱们学校开设了
an art course.
艺术的课程班
Interested students
感兴趣的同学呢
can come to me after class
下课以后可以到我这里
for the application form,
来拿报名表
get it signed by your parents at home.
回家以后找家长签字
This course
另外这个课程班呢
is voluntary.
是自愿的
A reminder:
老师嘱咐一句啊
art exams are not an easy way out.
艺考绝对不是捷径
So,
所以我希望同学们
think carefully,
可以仔细想清楚
discuss with your parents
回家以后呢
before applying.
跟家长商量再报名
Okay, class begin.
好 上课
Stand up.
起立
Hello, teacher.
老师好
How's Ms. Guo feeling today?
郭女士今天心情如何
Partly cloudy, turning sunny.
多云转晴
Quite bright.
还算明媚
What's up?
干嘛呢
Mom, can I help you with the veggies?
妈 要不我帮您洗洗菜
What is it this time?
闯祸了
No, not at all.
没有啊
Then what is it?
那有什么事啊
I...
我
I want to...
我想
What is it?
到底什么事啊
I want to learn painting.
我想学画画
Never mind.
没什么
I'll go do my homework.
我回屋写作业去了
Go ahead.
去吧
Doudou,
豆豆
what if my mom
我妈要是不同意
says no to painting?
我学画画怎么办啊
I'm so scared she'll reject me.
我好怕她拒绝我
Life's paintbrush
人生的画笔
is in your own hands.
是掌握在自己手中的
How will you know if you don't try?
不去试试怎么知道
The senior is right.
学姐说得对
Life's paintbrush
人生的画笔
is in your own hands.
掌握在自己手中
How will you know if you don't try?
不试一下怎么知道
Mom!
妈
What?
干什么呢
I want to apply for the art exam.
我想报美术艺考
No way.
不行
Mom, my dear mom,
妈 我的好妈妈
didn't you want me
你不是以前
to learn painting before?
也让我学画画的吗
That was
妈妈让你学画画是让你
to cultivate an interest,
培养你的兴趣爱好
not make it a career,
不是以画画为生
much less be a painter.
更不是当画家
What's wrong with being a painter?
当画家怎么了呀
Dad's a painter,
爸爸不也是画家吗
and our family is fine.
咱家也不比别人过得差
Right, Dad?
是不是 爸爸
Actually, I think...
其实我觉得吧
Xiao Datu!
肖大图
When I'm talking to our daughter,
我在教育女儿的时候
don't interrupt.
你少插嘴
You continue.
请继续
Sweetie,
宝贝啊
one artist in the family,
我们家有你爸爸
your dad, is enough.
这么一个画家就足够了
You don't need to get involved.
你就别掺和了行吗
You are a student.
你现在是学生
Your job now is to
最主要是什么
focus on the college entrance exam,
就是高考学习
study, and study more.
这才是你的王道
Go back to your room and study.
现在马上回房去读书
But the college entrance exam
可是高考也不是
isn't the only way.
唯一的方法是不是
People need dreams.
人总是要有梦想的
Without dreams, what's the
没有梦想
difference from being a salted fish?
那跟咸鱼有什么区别呢
Painting is my dream.
画画就是我的梦想
I've never
我从来都没有
felt this strongly.
想法这么强烈过
My dear mom,
我的好妈妈
please let me.
你就同意吧
Xiaohua,
小画 小画
be rational.
你脑子清楚一点好不好
Look at you,
你看看你刚才那样
talking non-stop.
叭叭叭说个没完了
Do you know what time it is?
都什么时候了
And you're still talking about dreams.
还要梦想梦想
What about dreams?
梦想怎么了
Can they feed you?
梦想能当饭吃啊
You're a student.
你现在是学生
Your job is to
学生干吗
study, study, and study more.
就是要读书读书再读书
The college entrance exam
高考
is your way out.
高考才是你出路啊
Why don't you understand?
你 你怎么不懂事啊
Go, study!
快快快 去读书
If you didn't
既然你这么不想
want me to paint,
让我学画画
why did you
那你当初为什么
name me Xiaohua?
要给我起这个名字
I know you're upset.
还哭呢
You know
你妈那个脾气
your mom's temper.
你还不知道啊
Handle her gently.
得顺着毛捋
Don't confront her.
不能硬刚
I didn't speak up
刚才爸爸不说话
to avoid making things worse.
那是怕火上浇油
Is this the application form?
这是报名表
Needs a signature, right?
得签字吧
There are two parents here.
这家长不有两个嘛
Besides your mom,
除了你妈
I'm here too.
你爸还在呢
Xiaohua,
小画
how did you
刚才
talk to your mom?
怎么跟你妈妈说话呢
Apologize
赶紧跟你妈妈
properly.
好好道个歉
Mom,
妈
I'm sorry.
对不起
I didn't mean
我刚刚
to speak like that.
不是有意要那么说的
What...
你说什么
What's there to apologize for?
有什么可道歉的
No overnight grudges.
母女之间哪有隔夜仇啊
All right, all right,
行了 行了
let's eat.
那个 吃饭吧
I'll make a few dishes.
妈妈做几个菜
Tomato stir-fry for dinner?
晚上吃西红柿炒番茄啊
So fancy.
这也太丰盛了吧
Fine,
行行行
it's not enough.
确实 确实不够啊
I'll go to the market and buy more food.
我去超市再买点菜
We'll have a proper meal tonight.
晚上好好地慰劳慰劳你
Well,
那
you all rest for a bit.
那你们先休息一会儿啊
Thank you.
辛苦了
Action.
行动
Dad,
爸
you've hidden so much pocket money.
你居然藏这么多私房钱
I'm going to tell Mom.
我要去告诉妈妈
Painting materials
这画画用的材料
cost money.
需要钱买
This is all I've got.
这是爸爸所有的家当了
Shh.
嘘
Okay.
嗯
Here are the study materials.
这个是艺考的复习资料
Only you two are going for the
咱班一共就你们两个
art entrance exam,
走艺考
so make sure
所以以后有什么问题呢
to help
我希望你们
each other out
可以互相请教
if you have any problems.
互相帮助
And,
还有
from this week,
这周呢
classes are
就是上课时间了
Monday to Friday
时间是每周一
after school
到周五的放学以后
and all day Saturday.
周六全天
If you're going to do it,
你们俩既然要学
be punctual
就好好学
and dedicated.
别迟到
Don't worry, Ms. Fang.
这点老师您放心
I will
我无论做什么
give it my all.
都会尽力做到最好
I'll work hard too.
我也会好好努力的
Also,
还有啊
in about a month,
差不多一个月以后呢
you'll have
就要开始
the proficiency test.
能力水平测验了
I believe
老师相信
you'll
这个考试对于你们来说
do great.
肯定没有问题
Thanks, Ms. Fang.
谢谢老师
Good luck.
加油
Mengyu,
梦予
what's usually on
能力水平测试
the proficiency test?
一般都考什么内容啊
You really have no clue, huh?
你这还真是盲考啊
I really
我觉得我自己
have no idea.
确实是什么都不懂
I just signed up out of passion.
凭着一腔热血就报名了
The proficiency test is the first step
能力水平测试呢
in our province's art exam.
是咱们省艺考的第一步
Passing it
通过了之后
is prerequisite for the provincial
才有机会参加之后的
and school exams.
省联考跟校考
Is it tough?
那会不会很难啊
It's not easy.
总之不会太简单
And
但对于
for those without a foundation,
没有什么基础的人来说
it can be challenging.
确实是有点难度的
Am I in trouble then?
那我不是惨了
This is just the start.
这才哪儿到哪儿啊
School exam and college entrance exam
之后的校考跟高考
are the real challenges.
才是真正的残酷呢
Aren't you passionate?
你不是一腔热血吗
Don't get discouraged now.
这就犯难了
I'll do my best.
我一定会尽全力的
You too.
你也加油
Of course.
那当然
I'm going to find Ms. Yu.
我去三楼找一下于老师
You go ahead.
你先走吧
Okay, bye.
好 拜拜
Bye.
拜拜
Congrats, apprentice.
恭喜徒弟
Now you can
这下你可以
focus on learning art.
安心地学美术了
This set of paints and art supplies
这盘颜料呢 跟画具
was chosen by Ling Dong
是我跟凌冬为你
and me.
精心挑选的
I also prepared
这也是我为你
this for you.
特意准备的
Friends,
朋友们
I'm determined to
我觉得考京大
get into Jing University!
我志在必得
Honey,
老婆
I've been standing for quite a while.
我站得挺久的
Can I take a break?
能中场休息一下吗
No!
不行
Stand straight!
立正
Stomach in!
收腹
Head up!
抬头
Xiao Datu,
肖大图同学
why did you
这么多年了
hide money from me
你为什么要欺骗我
all these years?
悄悄地藏私房钱呢
What examples are you setting
对孩子产生什么影响
for our child?
做了什么榜样
Mom,
妈
isn't this...
这 这
understandable?
这也是可以理解的吧
Right?
是吧
Understandable?
这怎么能够理解呢
Sweetie,
宝贝
in our warm,
我们家多么温暖
pure home?
多么纯粹
How can there be deceit?
怎么可以有欺骗的呢
You know,
你说说
mommy loves everyone so much.
妈妈是多爱大家呀
By the way,
对了
I've signed you up
妈妈特意用心
for a tutoring class.
给你报了一个补习班
It starts this week.
这个星期就上课
Of course,
当然了 这中间
thanks to your dad's
也有你爸爸的功劳
hidden money,
正好他的私房钱充公了
we could pay the tuition.
交了学费
Xiaohua,
小画
thank your dad for his efforts.
谢谢你爸的用心良苦
Thanks, Dad.
爸 我谢谢你啊
Study hard.
好好学习
Okay.
嗯
Stand straight!
立正
Stomach in!
收腹
The art class
美术培训班
overlaps with
跟名师辅导班
the master tutoring class.
时间刚好撞上
What now?
怎么办
I have an idea.
我有一个办法
Split yourself in two.
劈成两半 两不耽误
Paint
又能好好画画
and fool your mom.
还能瞒住妈妈
Great idea.
好主意
Show me how to split first.
你先分一个我看看
I was joking.
它就是开一种玩笑
Have some humor sense.
能不能有点幽默感
Xiaohua,
小画
is your tutoring class
你那个名师辅导班
on campus or off-campus?
是在校内还是校外
Off-campus.
在校外
Mom gave me
我妈给了我一张学生卡
a student card
说到时候拿着卡
to use.
直接去上课就行
That's easier.
那就好办很多了
Just get someone
你直接找个人
to go for you.
替你上课就行了
Yeah,
对啊
no one
反正是在校外不是吗
knows you off-campus.
没有人认识你肖小画
Have someone
找个人替一下
stand in for you.
不就得了吗
Impressive.
鬼斧神工啊
Flawless.
毫无破绽
Indeed.
确实
Really?
真的吗
Say something.
你再说句话试试
I'm Xiao Xiaohua.
我是肖小画
Well...
这
The voice is rough,
声音虽然有些粗犷
but passable.
但是勉强还可以解释
Stand up and let's see.
来 你站起来看看
Too tall.
太高了
Qingtian,
晴天
looks like it's up to you.
看来我还得靠你了
She?
靠她
Why didn't you say so earlier?
那你为什么不早说
Are you setting me up?
我怀疑你们在整我
Hmm,
嗯
I thought that was obvious.
不用怀疑
Feel the
大家落笔的时候
pen's weight
一定要感受一下
when drawing.
笔的轻重
Don't make heavy strokes.
不要画得那么笨
Xiao Xiaohua did well.
肖小画同学画得很好啊
Everyone, you can
大家下课之后呢
check her sketch
可以过来看一下
after class.
她的素描
Morning, daughter.
女儿 早啊
Morning, Dad.
早 老爸
Hmm?
嗯
Breakfast is simple today?
今天早饭这么简单
I'll tell Mom.
我要去告诉妈妈
Shh,
嘘
breakfast is fancy.
早饭特别得丰盛
Hmm.
嗯
Where's your mom?
那话说你妈呢
She went to buy groceries.
她去买菜了
Oh.
哦
I'm done. I'm leaving.
然后我吃完了 走了
Wait.
唉
Where are you going?
去哪儿啊
To the tutoring class.
我去补课啊
Right, tutoring.
哦 补课
Eat more, keep your strength up.
多吃点 先补补身体
I'm on a diet.
哎呀减肥
Bye.
我走了啊
Why diet at your age?
年纪轻轻减什么肥啊
Bye-bye.
拜拜
Study well.
好好补啊
Xiaohua.
小画
What?
嗯
Ling Dong,
凌冬
what brings you here?
你怎么来了
Xia Qingtian has something at home.
夏晴天家里有事
I'll be delivering your art supplies.
这几天我来给你送画具
That's kind of you.
那麻烦你了
It's no trouble, really. It's on my way.
没事 反正也顺路
Let me carry the supplies.
那我来拿画具
No need, I've got it.
不用 我帮你拿着吧
Let's go.
走
Thanks.
谢谢
The photo's blurry,
照片很模糊
can't see the face well.
看不到正脸
But he seems pretty handsome,
不过应该蛮帅的
reminds me of my younger days.
有我当年的风范
Can you be serious?
搞什么呀你
Hmm?
嗯
Where are you going?
你干嘛去啊
Going to check Xiaohua's room for clues.
去小画房间找找线索啊
Oh.
哦
Wait,
唉唉
I'm coming too.
我也去 我也去
Hey,
哎呀哎呀
honey,
老婆
this is...
这这这
this is our daughter's room.
哎呀 这女儿房间
Come on,
哎呀
we shouldn't rummage through it.
咱 咱别乱翻了吧
It's not proper.
不太好
I'm just checking.
我就看看
No-nothing special.
没 没东西啊
Nothing.
没有
See?
你看看
What are you doing?
这干吗
No.
哎呀
It's...
不太好 这
It's not good!
哎呀哎呀哎呀
Honey, honey.
老婆 老婆
Honey.
老 哎呦
Honey. Hon...
老婆 老
Xiao Datu!
肖大图
Look what it is!
你看这是什么
Wow!
哇
Is it a sketch of our daughter?
这女儿的画的随笔啊
Brilliant!
画得真好
Look at those facial lines.
你看这面部的线条
So clean, so smooth.
干净流畅
She inherited my good qualities.
很有我的风范哪
I mean,
我的意思是说
it's nice for her to draw in spare time.
没事画一画挺好的
It helps to relieve stress.
可以缓解学习的压力
Drawing?
什么画画不画画的
Am I talking about drawing?
重点是画画吗
This girl is in love!
女儿她早恋了
What?
啊
Look, look!
你看 你看
Oh.
哦
Oops.
哎呦
Which one of these two brats
这 这两个男生哪个
is our daughter's
才是那个拱白菜的
crush?
臭小子呀
Whoever isn't okay!
哪个都不行
It's almost time for
你说说马上就要高考了
the college entrance exam, and she
她把心思花在
is obsessed with all this nonsense.
这些有的没的身上
How would she be able to
怎么可以
concentrate on her study?
全身心地去学习呢
Well, honey.
老婆 你看吧
All of the teenagers
孩子吧
have issues during this period.
青春期都有这样的问题
Weren't we like this
咱年轻的时候
when we were young?
不也这样吗
Do you want me to talk to her?
要不我去找小画聊聊
No.
不行
We can't alarm her.
不能打草惊蛇
We should plan it carefully.
咱们得徐徐图之
Mom, I'm going out.
妈 我出门了
Are you going to the tutoring class?
去补习班
Yeah, yeah.
对啊 对啊
I'm off.
我走了
Okay.
好
Ling Dong.
凌冬
Hello.
来了
You've been waiting long?
你 你等很久了吗
I should have
早知道
come here earlier.
我就再早一点出门
It's alright. I just got here.
没有 我也是刚到
Let's go.
走吧
Let me take this.
我来拿吧
It's okay. It's not heavy.
没事 没多重
Come on. Get on.
走 先上车
Be careful.
唉 小心
Mom. Dad.
爸 妈
You both are here.
你们都在
You're in a good mood, huh?
心情不错啊
How's your tutoring?
补课补得怎么样啊
It's good.
我觉得挺好的
The teacher's lecture was lively.
老师讲课特别生动
I think
我觉得
it might work well.
应该挺有效果的吧
Are there any other bo...,
那你们有没有别的男
classmate of yours?
同学一起补课呀
Other classmates?
别的同学
No.
没有啊
Don't you have a study partner
那你不是跟有个同学
with one of
组成了一个
your classmates?
学习什么小组
He didn't go to tutoring with you?
他没跟你一块去补课啊
I've improved my grades,
我这不是成绩进步了嘛
so Ms. Fang said there's
方老师就没让我们
no need to continue.
继续了
That classmate of yours,
那 那个男同学
what's his name again?
叫什么来着
Ling Dong.
凌冬
Did you go to his place
那你寒假的时候
for tutoring over the winter break?
是到他家去补课的
No.
不是 不是
It was Lan Jinghui's place.
我去的是兰靖灰家
A boy is teaching you,
一个男同学给你补课
and another boy let you
你去另外一个
study in his place.
男同学家里
Which one is the one?
那到底是哪一个呢
The one?
什么哪个
It's not... I'm thinking...
不是 是这样的
That Ling Dong,
那个凌冬啊
and
还有那个
Lan Jinghui.
兰靖灰
Yeah.
对
I want to invite them over
妈妈想叫他们两个人
for dinner.
都到家里来吃饭
I'll prepare a feast.
给他们做好吃的
What?
啊
What's wrong?
怎么了
I don't understand.
不 不是
Why do you want
为什么要叫他们俩
to invite them for dinner?
来咱们家吃饭
It's not hard to understand.
那很正常嘛
It's so nice of them
人家帮你补课
to help you with the study.
对你那么好
I should thank them.
妈妈应该表示感谢一下
Yes.
对呀
They severed you at the last New Year eve.
你还在别人家过年
They treated you so well.
那么麻烦人家
That's why
那咱们家
we should express appreciation.
也要有所表示嘛
It is a deal!
就这么愉快地决定了啊
You can go now.
去吧
Yeah!
耶
You've been
你从刚才就用这种
looking at us
双目含泪
with hesitation
欲说还休的这种姿态
since a while ago.
看我们俩半天了
Spit it out.
说吧
What do you want?
说出你的愿望
I have a teeny-weeny,
我有一个小小 小小
itsy-bitsy wish.
小小的请求
I can grand it as long as
只要不犯法违纪
it's legal and reasonable.
其他都可以
This wish
这个请求
is definitely legal and reasonable.
既不犯法也不违纪
And it can fill your bellies.
还能填饱你们的肚子
It's a good deal.
这个买卖只赚不赔
That is to
就是
come over for dinner this Friday.
这周五去我家吃饭
Let's go through the battle plan
复习一下今晚的
for this evening.
作战计划
We'll use cuisine
用美食
to break down their defenses.
瓦解敌人心理防线
Use words to unravel the truth.
用聊天拼出真相的碎片
We'll find out
找出到底是谁
who our daughter's crush is
跟咱家闺女早恋
and SLASH! Work done.
然后啪 斩断红线
No more puppy love.
打碎情感萌芽
Perfect.
完美
Yeah.
耶
First of all,
首先啊
we need to find out
我们要找到
who knows her likes and dislikes.
谁知道咱家姑娘的口味
Then,
然后
we'll find who serves her.
看谁给咱家姑娘夹菜
Don't worry.
放心吧
What's that famous detective's name?
那个侦探叫什么来着
Formalin.
福尔马林
Then I can be "Xiaormalin".
那么我就是福尔肖马林
No.
什么呀
It's Holmes.
福尔摩斯
Get more education.
你有没有文化
Xiao Datu, Xiao Datu.
肖大图 肖大图
Draw less, read more books.
你少画点画 多看点书
OK?
好吗
Gosh.
真是
Do your work!
切菜
I've been thinking,
话说
what happened to your hand, mister?
叔叔 你手怎么了
My wrist's sprained.
扭了一下
Right.
行
Thank you again
那就再次感谢叔叔阿姨
for inviting us for dinner
邀约我们两个
at your home.
来家里吃饭
Shall we start?
那我们俩就先不客气了
Thank you so much.
谢谢叔叔阿姨
Help yourselves!
吃起来 吃起来
Okay, okay.
好好好
Here, try this snow pea.
来 吃点这个荷兰豆
It looks so delicious.
看上去就很好吃的样子
It's good for intestinal activity
促进肠道蠕动
and your skin.
而且还能修肤养肌
Here.
来
Try this.
你也别闲着
The pork chop
这个排骨
looks so delicious.
看起来做得就特别好吃
Try more meat.
多吃点肉
Meat is always the main dish!
肉才是王道
What's going on?
这什么情况
Why neither of them
他们怎么
serve our daughter?
不给咱姑娘夹菜啊
They must be pretending.
肯定不能那么明显
Just wait for it.
咱们再观察观察
Lan Jinghui.
来 兰靖灰
Try this streaky bacon.
吃块五花肉
Let me serve you.
这个远你夹不着
Thanks.
谢谢
Ling Dong, try this.
凌冬 你也吃一块
Does this mean
难道我们家闺女
she's into both of them?
还惦记两个
I hope today's dinner
不知道今天阿姨做的菜
is to your liking.
合不合你们胃口啊
Here, try this.
来 你吃点这个尝尝
Wait!
唉
Hold on, mom.
妈 等一下
Ling Dong dislikes cilantro or chili.
凌冬他不吃香菜和辣椒
I told you.
我说的吧
This boy is the one.
这个有情况
But Lan Jinghui likes them.
不过 兰靖灰喜欢
Yes.
没错
Cilantro and chili
没有香菜跟辣椒
are the souls of a meal.
就没有灵魂
This one may be the one, too.
好像这个也有情况
No worries.
没事
There's been a glitch
我们家线路
in electricity for a while.
经常有点问题
Xiaohua,
女儿
Jinghui's families must have paid extra efforts
你寒假到别人家去补课
to take care of you
一定是
during the winter break.
麻烦人家的家长了吧
No.
没有
It's okay, ma'am.
不麻烦 阿姨
My grandma likes her so much
我奶奶特别喜欢肖小画
that she wishes she'd come every day.
巴不得她天天去
Pay more attention to this one.
重点怀疑对象
Well,
那
you must live far from school.
你家一定离学校不近吧
Yeah, kind of.
反正是挺远
Do you usually take the bus
那平时到学校的时候
or the subway
是坐公交
to school?
还是坐地铁
I mostly
我呢
go by bike.
主要是骑自行车去
It's fast.
特别快
No way.
不对啊
Ling Dong, you must be taking the bus
凌冬 那你上学的时候
to school, right?
肯定是坐公交 对不对
No, ma'am.
没有啊 阿姨
I take the bike, too.
我也是骑车上学的
Mom!
哎呀
What are you doing?
妈 你干什么呀
You ask too much.
问东问西的
They'll mistake you as policewoman.
搞人口普查呢
Let them have their meal.
让不让人好好吃饭了
Go back to dinner.
吃饭
Dad, bon appétit.
爸 你也吃
Okay, go back to dinner.
吃饭 吃饭 吃饭
Dinner, dinner.
吃饭了 吃饭了 吃饭了
Right, right.
吃 吃
Help yourselves.
吃饭 吃饭啊
Don't rush.
慢点 慢点 慢点
I'm full. I don't want to
再跑胃下垂了
get gastroptosis.
刚吃完饭
You're so weak.
你这小体格不行啊
Is it just me, or your mom
你不觉得
was trying to get something from us?
阿姨在套我们话吗
I'm sure about it.
不用觉得 就是
I knew it!
是吧
You feel something suspicious, too.
你们也觉得不对劲
Is there something wrong
我妈她是不是
with my mom?
哪里怪怪的
But
可是
what for?
那阿姨是为了点什么呢
There must be something wrong.
事出反常必有妖
She's been strange
自从我补
since the day I came back
补课回来那天
from tutoring.
她就变得怪怪的
Does that mean
难道
she's found out that you are
难道是她发现了你在外边
learning to draw?
学画画的事
If she knew,
那阿姨发现了
why hadn't she just asked you?
为什么不直接戳穿你啊
She's probably just getting suspicious.
她可能只是刚开始怀疑
Why don't you ask your dad
那你就不会跟叔叔
if he knows one thing
打探打探消息
or two.
套套他的话
If he really knew something,
我爸要是知道什么
he would've told me.
他肯定会跟我通气的呀
He and I are on the same side.
我跟他是同一条战线的
Then
那现在
there's only one way left.
就只有一个办法了
What is it?
什么办法
Put your mom's concerns to rest.
打消阿姨的顾虑
Easy to say.
你说得容易
How to do it?
怎么操作
Come.
来
I'll tell you.
跟你说
How do you think
你说
who the bus boy is?
那个公交男到底是谁呀
I don't think either of them are.
我看他俩都不太像
Put your hand down.
把手放下来
You really think you're Formalin?
你真以为你福尔马林呢
Holmes.
福尔摩斯
They both seemed normal.
确实也很正常啊
There's nothing odd about them.
看不出什么异样来
Honey,
老婆
how do you think
你觉得
both of them?
这两个男孩怎么样
I think they're good boys.
我觉得都挺好的
I think,
我觉得
that Lan Jinghui is good.
那个兰靖灰挺好的
He's nice. He's a sweet talker.
性格好 嘴又甜
But I think Ling Dong is better.
我倒觉得凌冬好
The boy
这人哪
is steady and calm.
稳重 沉得住气
He can do great things in the future.
将来一看就能干大事
He's too calm
小孩子家家的
for a kid.
心思太沉不太好
They're not that young.
都不小了
If he can't remain calm now,
毛毛躁躁的
how will he be in the future?
将来成什么样子
Nonsense.
什么呀
They're teenagers.
现在是青春的时候嘛
They're bound to be lively.
所以啊 要朝气蓬勃
Nonsense.
什么呀
One's fate can be seen from childhood.
小就可以看到老
If one can't remain calm from a young age,
小时候就不稳重
they won't be successful in the future.
将来能干什么呀
Just like you.
就像你一样
You see,
你看
What's about me?
我又怎么了呢
You keep fidgeting,
你一直活泼活泼
unlike a grown-up.
不成样子
What's it got to do with me?
你怎么又谈到我了呢
It's none of my...
我又怎么了
You never take my advice!
你从来就没听过我
I tell you!
我告诉你
Xiao Datu!
肖大图
Honey.
老婆
What's wrong?
怎么了
Go wash dishes.
洗碗去
Go have your shower.
洗澡去
You're so clever.
老辣
Cleverer than ever.
辣哥
Then I'll go home now. Bye!
那我先回去了 拜拜
Bye. Bye.
拜拜 拜拜
Bye.
拜拜
Safe travels.
注意安全
Okay.
好
Which one of us do you think
你觉得叔叔阿姨
her parents like better?
更喜欢咱们俩谁啊
Isn't it obvious?
那还用想吗
Sure.
也是
It's me, of course!
肯定是我呀
You're so cocky!
你也太不要脸了吧
I would say it's me!
我还觉得是我呢
Didn't you notice
你就没看到
how her mom looked at me?
阿姨看我的眼神吗
Then didn't you notice
那你是没看到
how happy her dad was
叔叔的眼神
when he looked at me,
看我的时候是眉头舒展
and how unhappy when he looked at you?
看你是眉头紧皱
No way!
哪有
Did you notice
那你有没有看到
she didn't let me do the dishes
吃完饭之后
after dinner because
阿姨都不让我刷碗
she didn't want me to get tired.
就是怕我累着
I even got an orange from him.
那叔叔还给我橘子了呢
Did you get one?
你有吗
She,
那 那阿姨
she even called me by my nickname.
还直接叫我小名了呢
So intimate.
多亲切
Yeah, you win the game.
是 你赢了好嘛
"Li'l Hui".
小灰灰
Don't lump things together.
一码是一码
It's got nothing to do
这跟小灰灰
with the name itself.
没有什么关系
What I mean
我给你
by giving you this example
举这个例子的意思
is that
就是说
I'm an easy-going person,
我这个人为人比较随和
and she got along better with me.
阿姨比较跟我好相处
But you can't call me that.
你直接叫我名字
They're,
这个东西
they're two different things,
这这这 两码事啊
you know?
你知道吧
It's not that easy to get into Hengyuan.
恒远哪是那么容易进的
It's normal to be out.
被淘汰了是正常
A tryout means
而且试训的意思就是说
to give it a try.
去试一试
You've tried and it showed
你已经试过了
you're better than me.
比我强
What's so great to be better than you?
比你强那不是很正常吗
I was just careless that day.
我那天只是大意了
I didn't lose that game.
那场比赛我没输啊
We'll see next year.
你不信明年你看着
Silly.
你傻呀
There're no more games for the 12th grade.
高三不参加比赛
Yeah, I forgot.
对啊 我给忘了
By the way,
对了
I heard you didn't show up for practice
听说我去试训的时候
when I tried out.
你一直没来训练
Right.
嗯
I didn't play anymore.
不玩了
I've tried.
试过了
I lost it.
输了
I can give you another chance.
来 给你个机会
We can fight a duel.
单挑
No regrets.
别留遗憾
Have you thought about the future?
你想过以后吗
I mean,
我是说
after high school?
高中毕业之后
No.
不知道啊
I probably keep playing basketball.
可能继续打球吧
I'm off.
走了
What's your plan for the future?
你以后什么打算啊
I want to go to university.
我想考大学
Jing University.
京大
Actually,
其实
you guys were pretty good that day.
你们那天发挥挺好的
If you'd gone to the tryouts,
如果你去试的话
you might have qualified.
说不定能留下来
Don't just practice alone anymore.
以后别老一个人练了
You need a partner.
需要陪打
Feel free to call me.
随时叫我
Cheers!
加油